So today's דף daf is דף ה, Daf Hey, and we pick
up at the bottom of דף ד עמוד ב, Daled Amud Beis,
and we're still working through the debate of רבה Rabba and רבא,
Rava, whether the reason of the משנה Mishnah is because of the
need for the to be able to ensure that the signatures are
validated, and we're concerned that if we don't do it now we
won't, אין עדים מצויים לקיימו, Ein Eidim Metzuyim Lekaymo, or whether to
ensure that the גט get was written properly, the issue of רבה
Rabba of לשמה. Lishma. And the גמרא's Gemara worked through interesting debates
in the משנה Mishnah where it could nicely have fallen along those
lines, but has managed to explain it according to each position.
Okay, and the sort of the current outstanding question there with the
משנה Mishnah was why ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael had a special status,
that within ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you don't have to say if
it's all about witnesses, and the answer is, well, there's a lot
of travel in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, either when there was a
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or even now because of the בתי דינים.
Batei Dinim. So we now have managed to sort of defend each
position. So now the גמרא Gemara continues at the bottom of דף
ד עמוד ב, Daled Amud Beis,
תנן, Tnan, it's ten lines from the bottom, line starts with the
word שכיחי. shchichi. Okay, so תנן, Tnan, we taught in the משנה,
Mishnah, moving our way through the משנה, Mishnah, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר, Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel Omer, אפילו מהגמוניא להגמוניא, Afilu Mehigmonya Lehigmonya,
even from one hegemonia to
another, which basically from a city that is divided, as we'll see
in a minute, between two governments. ואמר רבי יצחק, V'amar Rabbi Yitzchak,
and רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak explained this, עיר אחת היתה בארץ ישראל,
Ir achas haysa b'Eretz Yisrael, there's a city in Israel, ואסיסיות שמה,
v'Asasyos shma, and the same was Asasyos, or a town, והיו שתי
הגמוניות, v'hayu shtei higmonyos,
and there were two separate governments שהיו מקפידים זה על זה, shehayu
makpidim zeh al zeh, that were, you know, sort of at odds
with one another.
And therefore you weren't able to travel, the point of מקפידים makpidim
is you weren't able to travel from one, from one side of
the city to the other, East and West Berlin. לפיכך הוצרכו לומר
מהגמוניא להגמוניא. Lefikach hutzrechu lomar mehigmonya lehigmonya.
Therefore that was the חידוש chiddush that even within one city, if
it's going from like one political entity from one city to the
next, from half of the city to the other half of the
city, you have to say. Now the key about this is is
that it's because of the presumably the impossibility of travel. And that
he says ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael was in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
So if it's ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, it's not a לשמה Lishma
concern. So this clearly shows that at least for רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל, Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel, it's an issue about witnesses and the
ability for to travel from one place to the next. So the
גמרא Gemara says לרבה ניחא לרבא קשיא, L'Rabba nichla L'Rava kashya, that's
good for רבא, Rava, it's difficult for רבה. Rabba. And it says
רבה אית ליה דרבא. Rabba islei d'Rava. So after all of that,
we come to the conclusion, alright fine, רבה Rabba concedes רבא's Rava
point. So the one who says לשמה Lishma also concedes that there's
a problem of אין עדים מצויים לקיימו. Ein Eidim Metzuyim Lekaymo. Now
why didn't it just say that that's רבן שמעון בן גמליאל's Rabban
Shimon Ben Gamliel position and maybe everybody else doesn't agree with it,
I don't know, but the גמרא Gemara here is saying that there's
a position that holds both that רבה Rabba is really רבה Rabba
plus רבא, Rava, which actually is a nice elegant position because, you
know, there's two parts of the statement, בפני נכתב, Bifnei Nichtav, where
you care about how it's written, and בפני נחתם, Bifnei Nechtam, you
care about how it's signed. So let's say that those are two
concerns. You care about how it's written because of לשמה, Lishma, and
you care because of whether it was written כהלכתה, kehilchasa, and you
care about how it's signed because of אין עדים מצויים לקיימו, Ein
Eidim Metzuyim Lekaymo, whether there's going to be about validating the signatures.
So now we have said that that is רבה's Rabba position. So
if that's רבה's Rabba position, if רבה Rabba agrees to רבא, Rava,
what are they debating about? And the answer is רבה Rabba agrees
to רבא, Rava, but רבא Rava doesn't agree to רבה. Rabba. So
the גמרא Gemara says אלא מאי בינייהו, Ella mai beinaihu, so now
what's left to be between them? Okay, everybody would agree you need
to have validate the signatures, so for example in one מדינה medina
in חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, everybody in מדינת הים, Medinas Hayam, everybody
would agree you need because even though there's or because, excuse me,
in one yeah, in one no, excuse me, if from one, well,
okay let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. I'm confusing myself. Okay
anyway, everybody agrees that the signatures is an issue, so what would
be a case where where they would debate whether there would be
a concern about the לשמה? Lishma? Right, because if now everybody agrees
the issue is validation of signatures, then the only נפקא מינה nafka
mina would be a case where you don't have to worry to
validate the signatures, but you still have to worry about לשמה. Lishma.
So what would be that case? So אלא מאי בינייהו אי נמי
דאתו בי תרי, Ella mai beinaihu ee nami d'asya b'trei, that two
people brought it. So two witnesses are bringing it, they themselves are
witnesses that the husband sent them. So there's no need to validate
the signatures in that case. Okay, but if they're coming from חוץ
לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, even if you have no questions that the husband
wrote the גט get and the גט get is valid, you still
have to worry about was it done כהלכתה. kehilchasa. So that would
be a case where there's no concern of signatures, but there is
a concern of לשמה. Lishma. אי נמי, Ee nami, or another example
is, באותה מדינה ממדינת הים, b'osam medina m'medinas hayam, in the same
country especially in מדינת הים Medinas Hayam
where there's no concern about signatures because it's the same country and
there's a lot of travel, but for רבה Rabba there still is
a concern of לשמה. Lishma. Okay, so whenever there's a concern about
validating signatures, everybody agrees you have to say it. רבה אית ליה
דרבא. Rabba islei d'Rava. רבה's Rabba just saying in addition I'm also
concerned of לשמה. Lishma. So even in cases where there's no concern
of signatures, I'll be concerned if there's a לשמה Lishma problem if
it's the type of a חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz problem.
Like in Spain where no Torah was ever learned.
Exactly.
So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
Okay, so that's now what they're debating. And as I said, the
nice thing about saying that you hold of both is that it
explains both נכתב ונחתם *nechtav v'nechtam*. תנן *Tnan*, the mishna. המביא גט
ממדינת הים Ha-mevi get mimedinas hayam, ואינו יכול לומר בפני נכתב ובפני
נחתם bifnai nichtav ubifnai nechtam *Hamavi get mimedinas hayam v'eino yachol lomar
bifnei nechtav uvifnei nechtam*. Now we're still going to see if we
can see this one thing out. המביא גט get? ממדינת הים mimedinat
hayam. ואינו יכול לומר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם bifnai nichtav ubifnai nechtam,
*Hamavi get mimedinas hayam v'eino yachol lomar bifnei nechtav uvifnei nechtam*. This
is a mishna later up. Somebody comes from מדינת הים Medinat Hayam,
*Medinas Hayam* and he's not able to say it was signed and
sealed in front of me. Now, if you tell me he's not
able to say it, what's your gut guess about why he's not
able to say it? Why can't he say it was signed and
sealed in front of
me, signed— I'm sorry, written and signed in front of me? Because
he wasn't? Right, he wasn't there. Okay, but somehow the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* understands that אינו יכול eino yachol, *eino yachol* means some way
he is like physically unable. So it's an interesting interpretation of the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Let's take a look. He's unable to say that,
so the mishna concludes by saying אם יש עליו עדים eidim. יתקיים
בחותמיו *im yesh alav eidim yiskayem b'chosamav*. No problem, even if you're
not able to say it, just get witnesses to validate the signatures.
Now that mishna is pretty darn clear that the whole real concern
is validating the signatures. You're not able to say this special, you
know, statement? Okay, validate the signatures and you're fine.
Which sounds like the whole point of this is validating the signatures.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ובהוינן בה *v'avinan bah*, now before
we get to that, we have to understand what אינו יכול *eino
yachol* means. And we asked about this. מאי אינו יכול לומר *mai
eino yachol lomar*? What does it mean he's unable to say? Top
of ה עמוד amud, א *Hey Amud Aleph*. אילימא חרש cheireish. *Ilima
cheresh*, if we're talking about a
deaf-mute, yeah, it's the first place I would have gone. Right. Okay,
so then חרש cheresh, בר אתויי גיטא הוא *cheresh bar asuyei gita
hu*? Can you make a deaf-mute a person to bring a גט
get, *get*? והתנן *v'hatnan*, הכל כשרים להביא את הגט חוץ מחרש שוטה
וקטן *hakol k'sherim l'havi es haget chutz micheresh shoteh v'katan*. Anybody can
bring a גט get *get* except for a deaf-mute, a minor, and
somebody who is like, let's just say that as not of right
mind. So that is, and that's because they can't be a שליח
shaliach *shaliach*. One of the important things we're going to be dealing
with with גיטין *Gittin* is laws of שליחות shlichus, *shlichus*. Okay, so
if somebody is not considered to be an adult of right mind,
they're not able to bring a גט get *get*. And this was
the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's* assumption as well about a חרש *cheresh*. He
wasn't a בר דעת *bar da'as*. That's a separate conversation, how that's
changed in the modern era because once, you know, in terms of
schools for the deaf and the whole thing. Anyway,
but that's the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's* assumption. So if that's the case,
how could he be bringing a גט get, *get*? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, ואמר רב יוסף *v'amar Rav Yosef*, הכא במאי עסקינן
Hacha bmai askinan? *hacha b'mai askinan*? So רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* explains,
what are we talking about here? כגון שנתנו לו כשהוא פיקח *k'gon
shenasno lo k'shehu pikei'ach*. Yeah, he gave it to her while he
was totally fine. ולא הספיק לומר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם bifnei nechtav
u-vifnei nechtam, *v'lo hispik lomar bifnei nechtav uvifnei nechtam*, and before he
could get the words out of his mouth of בפני נכתב ובפני
נחתם bifnei nechtav u-vifnei nechtam. *bifnei nechtav uvifnei nechtam* after he delivered
the גט get *get*, עד eid, שנתחרש *ad shenischaresh*, all of a
sudden something happened and he became a deaf-mute. He had a stroke
on the spot. Okay, so that's the example. So therefore, that's why
he's unable to say. It's very strange again why the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* just does not just say that he did not witness it.
Anyway, or how about an easier answer? Look at תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*.
You know what, if you're already talking about a physical inability, why
do you go to a חרש *cheresh* who's considered not a בר
דעת *bar da'as*? There's somebody else who can't say something who is
a בר דעת *bar da'as*, which is somebody who's just
mute, right? ודלא בעא למימר כגון אלם *v'lo ba'a l'meimar k'gon ilem*?
How about somebody who is mute? או שלא ראה כתיבת הגט *o
shelo ra'ah kesivas haget*? Or somebody who just happened not to have
seen it, okay? Those would have been two much more easier explanations
and you wouldn't have had to have this very extreme case. ואם
כן הוה ליה למימר ולא אמר *v'im kein hava lei l'meimar v'lo
amar*. It should have just said, 'and he didn't say'. Unable to
say seems like we're emphasizing something about his complete, somehow halachic inability.
I don't know, both of those would have seemed to have been
much easier explanations. Okay, that either he's just mute or he actually
didn't see. Either way, the point is somebody delivered a גט get
*get* and wasn't able to or didn't say בפני נכתב bifnai nichtav
*bifnei nechtav*, and the solution is just go ahead and get witnesses
to validate, which makes it pretty clear that there's only one concern
going on here.
Yeah, תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says, this guy didn't see, that's what it
means 'he can't say'. Or if it has to be a physical
inability, say he's a mute, not that he's a deaf-mute. All right,
so anyway, we don't know why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* didn't go
that way. Doesn't matter for us right now. What matters for us
is the guy didn't say it and the solution is just go
ahead and get witnesses. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
לרבא ניחא לרבה קשיא *l'Rava nicha l'Rabba kashya*. It's good for רבא
Rava *Rava* because the only concern is witnesses, but for רבה Rabbah.
*Rabba* it's difficult. Whatever happened to the לשמה lishma. *lishma* concern? The
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אה Ah, *ah*, הכא במאי עסקינן *hacha b'mai
askinan*? לאחר שלמדו l'achar she'lamdu, *l'achar shelamdu*. Ah, what are we talking
about here? We're talking about after in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz, *chutz
l'aretz* they learned the need for לשמה lishma *lishma* and the הלכה
halacha *halacha* changed. So it's very strange, right? You start out with
this nice big fundamental debate. Is it about... or is it about
לשמה. lishma Then you have some pretty heavy evidence that it's for
about witnesses. So we say, okay, רבא Rava holds of רבה. Rabbah
Okay, but then you have even more evidence that it's not about
לשמה. lishma, So then we say, okay, well רבה Rabbah would concede
that there became a time where לשמה lishma fell by the wayside.
So basically sort of saying, okay, so רבא Rava. sort of won.
Okay, you have to say רבה Rabbah agrees with him and רבה
Rabbah even agrees that there was a time where his concern fell
by the wayside, presumably that's the הלכה halacha, changed around this issue,
which is something we're going to look at, which is does the
need of from where you're saying and to say בפני נכתב ובפני
נחתם bifnei nichtav u-bifnei nechtam, change where, you know, in changing circumstances?
Okay, so we will see about that as we continue, but the
גמרא Gemara, here is at least conceding that at least to some
degree it does, and now רבה Rabbah really has completely become like
רבא. Rava Now having said that, we will see when we turn
the עמוד, not to ruin the surprise anyway, that other אמוראים Amoraim
debate whether it's לשמה lishma, or about אין עדים מצויין לקיימו, ein
eidim metzuyin lekaymo, and some seem to say really, no, it's only
about לשמה, lishma okay, do not seem to have been, you know,
sort of reworked through the גמרא Gemara here. And the question is
like, you know, maybe some of these things, like you could say
and תוספות Tosafot at one point concedes like, well, maybe it's מחלוקת
תנאים, machlokes Tannaim, like maybe, you know, he before anyway, the only
thing that pushed us to say רבה Rabbah agreed with רבא Rava.
was a statement of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel.
All right, so that was רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel. Okay, here you have a משנה, Mishnah, that this משנה Mishnah
is pretty clear that it's all about the signatures, but you know,
again, why do we have to assume that all these תנאידיק Tannaidic
material is all of one position? All right, but the גמרא Gemara
here is sort of bringing it all together and saying basically רבה
Rabbah. has turned into רבא. Rava I will remind us that the
evidence to point to רבה'ס Rabbah's position is the emphasis on ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. If it's all about witnesses, there should be no
special emphasis on ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So the emphasis on ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael that it's fundamentally when it comes from חוץ לארץ,
chutz la'aretz, fundamentally in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael there's no problem, that's
the big evidence that weighs for רבה. Rabbah So if you just
look at what the evidence in front of you, yes you've got
a lot of stuff that says it's all about witnesses, but there
is other things that makes רבה Rabbah say his position, the emphasis
on ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Yes, which brings us going back to that other point, in other
words, it's moving more to a contextual rather than a formalistic position.
In other words, okay, New York and New Jersey, with, well,
that's what I said, the parameters might change.
Right, the parameters might change. Now, how much they change case by
case, you know, every time, like, yes, meaning we'll continue to pay
attention to that. But this is definitely showing you that it's possible
the parameters change, and if there's a time when לשמה lishma, stops
being a concern, for רבה Rabbah at least you now, for, it
doesn't mean you don't have to say, it means that that stops
being one of the concerns. So for example, you know, all you'd
have to worry about in this case would be to validate it
with witnesses. So now the גמרא Gemara continues and says the following:
okay, לאחר שלמדו, le'achar shelamdu, so רבה Rabbah, holds of רבא Rava
and he holds that there is a time in the תנאידיק Tannaidic
period where it stopped being a, his issue stopped being a concern
and all we're left with is the issue of עדים. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי, ei hachi, that's true, יכול נמי.
yachal nami. So why does it sound like, you know, you really
should be saying בפני נכתב bifnai nichtav. ובפני נחתם, but it's נבח,
nebech, if you can't, then you know, it's okay to get, to
validate the signatures? Okay, why don't we just say from the beginning,
you know what, if you want to validate signatures be my guest,
that's even better, right? So why do we set it up like
it seems like there's a preference to say בפני נכתב bifnai nichtav
if now everybody knows about לשמה, lishma, so that should no longer
be an issue of concern? Just לכתחילה lechatchila go ahead and validate
if you want to do that. And then the question, yeah, like
it's structured like it says if it's really not possible to say
it, then you can go ahead and validate the signatures. Well, if
there's no longer a לשמה lishma issue, just tell me, if you
want to validate the signatures instead of saying it, you know, be
my guest. So why does it sound like you're really supposed to
say it? So the גמרא Gemara says גזירה שמא יחזור הדבר לקלקולו.
gezeira shema yachzor hadavar lekilkulo. No,
and here goes the issue about how contextual it is and how
much does it change. Right, where we don't want to לכתחילה lechatchila
say you don't have to say because we want to לכתחילה lechatchila
keep things in their place. Initially there was a concern of לשמה,
lishma who knows, things got better, things might get worse, things do
change. We noticed that they just changed recently. So therefore, you always
need to keep on saying it. What we will say is בדיעבד,
bedieved, if you're not able to say it, we'll acknowledge the current
circumstances, okay? But לכתחילה lechatchila we're going to keep things the way
they used to be and we want you to say בפני נכתב.
bifnai nichtav But if that's not possible, just validate the signatures. So
the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי, ei hachi, אינו יכול נמי? eino
yachol nami? So if that's true, that we want to keep things
the way they used to be, we should insist on it even
in a case where he's not able to say. Now again, the
obvious answer is what I just said, there's a little bit of
a difference between לכתחילה lechatchila and בדיעבד, bedieved, but the גמרא Gemara
says... if you really want to keep things the old ways, even
if you're even if you're dealing with this guy who's not able
to say, there should be no out. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, פיקח ונשתתק מילתא לא שכיחא. Pikeiach v'nishtateik milta lo shechiha. Now
maybe this is why it was important to establish that we were
not just dealing with a guy who didn't see, the... but somebody
this bizarre case of the person who became a חרש. That's a
very
unusual circumstance, ומילתא דלא שכיחא לא גזרו בה רבנן. u'milta d'lo shechiha
lo gazru bah rabanan. And therefore we could say that the fact
that we insisted like that we made a לא פלוג lo plug
and we insisted that you continue saying it even though there's no
concern of לשמה, lishma we didn't apply that to bizarre cases. So
therefore that's why you don't have to worry about it in this
bizarre case. גמרא Gemara, says one minute, every case that's unusual you
don't have to worry about
it? והא אשה דלא שכיחא, V'ha isha d'lo shechiha, how about when
a woman brings a גט? get דתנן, D'tnan, האשה עצמה מביאה גיטה.
ha'isha atzma meivia gita. A woman can even bring her own גט,
get, okay which is very bizarre, how does she not... what's exactly
the point? It is another bizarre case. How does she not become
divorced the minute the גט get. reaches her hand? And the גמרא
Gemara? says what's a case that the husband said I'm making you
a שליח shliach to bring the גט get to yourself when you
get to this town. Okay, so anyway, completely bizarre case, okay, and
that's okay, ובלבד שצריכה לומר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. u'vilvad she'tzricha lomar
bifnai nichtav u'vifnai nechtam. But she also has to testify it was
written and signed in front of me. So therefore,
how can you so... look, why don't we just say we don't...
no that's the answer. Why don't we why don't we just say
that we don't require this in bizarre cases? So the גמרא, Gemara
just there also just validate the signatures, why do we require the
בפני נכתב bifnai nichtav? line? So the גמרא Gemara says שלא תחלוק
בשליחות. Shelo tachlok b'shlichus. No, going back to its center what its
old answer was, לא פלוג, lo plug, we don't want to make
distinctions. We want to insist that everybody says it. Okay, but now
we're sort of like going in a circle. So then so then
if that's true, back to back to the old question which is,
how about the guy that became a deaf mute? Why don't you
say buddy you gotta say it? So the bottom line the answer
is, is that we basically make a לא פלוג, lo plug, we
keep things the way they are, we say it doesn't matter if
it's a usual standard case or an unusual case, we don't want
to let you just validate the signatures, we want you to say
בפני נכתב bifnai nichtav? because that was the old way of doing
it because that addressed the לשמה lishma. concerns. And the reason the
case of the deaf mute is different is because there's no option.
And if you look, תוספות Tosafot just says in one line, שלא
תחלוק בשליחות, shelo tachlok b'shlichus, this little תוספות Tosafot before like ten
lines before they get
why, פירוש בשליחות דיכול. peirush b'shlichus d'yachol. When you're able to do
it, we're going to insist that you do it. Okay, whether it's
a normal case or a not normal case. But when you're not
able to do it, we'll accept the new realities and we'll say
okay, you're not able to do it, we'll accept that really nowadays
is not a לשמה lishma concern, just validate the signatures and you'll
be fine.
Yes, you sound like you've constructed the argument that way in order
to lay these formal principles, because it's a bizarre comparison, a guy
who was healthy and then and then suddenly in the middle of
testifying has a stroke to a woman. Women are שכיחא. shechiha.
Well, not a woman bringing her own גט, get, but okay. It
was a woman bringing her own גט get? with a bizarre condition.
All right, anyway, moving on though. The
point... the point is, לכתחילה l'chatchila for רבה, Rabbah you're supposed to
say it. לכתחילה L'chatchila for רבה Rabbah you're supposed to say it
to keep things the old way because there was a לשמה lishma.
concern that might become one again, but when there's no choice, you
acknowledge the current realities and it's okay just to validate the signatures.
תוספות Tosafot of course points out that this is so strange because
רבא Rava would would say that there's no לכתחילה l'chatchila at all.
רבא Rava. would of course be happy if you just validated the
signatures and you didn't have to say it. So why does the
גמרא Gemara think for רבה Rabbah it has to be a לכתחילה?
l'chatchila? But anyway, that's what the גמרא Gemara is assuming. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
בעל נמי, Ba'al nami, how about by the husband, when he there's
not even a case of שליחות, shlichus when he's delivering the גט
get himself? אלמה תניא, Alama tanya, why do we teach in a
ברייתא, braita, הוא עצמו שהביא גטו אין צריך לומר בפני נכתב ובפני
נחתם. Hu atzmo sheheivi gito ein tzarich lomar bifnai nichtav u'vifnai nechtam.
If he's bringing his own גט get from מדינת הים, Medinat Hayam,
he doesn't have to say it. So, I mean, look, we understand
again there's no concern of signatures because he's not he's bringing it,
he's not going to claim it was forged if he himself is
delivering it, but maybe he could still claim that oh, I didn't
realize you were supposed to write it לשמה. lishma So as long
as he's bringing it from מדינת הים, why according to רבה Rabbah
should we not insist that he continue to say בפני נכתב? bifnai
nichtav So and if you tell me that they now they know
the הלכה, halacha but let's be afraid that things will slide back.
So why don't we continue to insist the husband say בפני נכתב?
bifnai nichtav That's a good question. So the גמרא Gemara says, right,
and this is not a case of אינו יכול, right everybody intended
this is a really good case. If for רבה Rabba, you're telling
me we want to keep things the old way and continue to
say בפני נכתב bifnei nechtav because we might because of לשמה lishma
concerns which might resurface, okay, then when a husband delivers a גט,
get. he should have to say בפני נכתב bifnei nechtav, because even
though he's giving it, he has to tell us that it was
done לשמה. lishma. Why do we not require... require that? So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. So
the גמרא Gemara says טעמא מאי אמרו רבנן צריך לומר בפני נכתב
ובפני נחתם. taama mai amru rabbanan tzarich lomar bifnei nechtav uvifnei nechtam.
No, says the גמרא, Gemara the reason you have to say בפני
נכתב בפני נחתם bifnei nechtav bifnei nechtam is דילמא אתי בעל ומערער
ופסיל ליה dilma ati baal umaarer upassilei because we're afraid the husband
is going to, you know, he's going to challenge it and he'll
invalidate it, which means we're not remember the first דף daf of
the גמרא? Gemara we're not really concerned it was done שלא לשמה.
shelo lishma. We basically don't even it's not even like a it's
like even a מיעוטא דמיעוטא, miuta demiuta, it's like a tiny littlest
concern that it was done שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. It's not a
real concern. The real concern is that the husband will use that
as an excuse to challenge the גט. get, But there's no genuine
concern it's שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. The real concern is the problems
the husband is going to make. So השתא, hashta, if that's true,
so מנא נקטי ליה בידיה ואתי קא מערער ליה? minka nakeitei biyadei
veatei kamaarer leh?
He's bringing it in his own hands and he's now going to
challenge it? Like if he himself is taking the effort to deliver
it himself, and he's also putting himself out there, you know, publicly
as the one who gave it if it all happened outside of
me, some שליח shaliach... went and delivered it in my name, I
could say I don't know what was happening and like you know,
and I can raise challenges because I'm not personally involved. If I'm
personally involved, the likelihood that I'm going to say, "Yes, I delivered
this גט get to my wife but it was done שלא לשמה,"
shelo lishma, right, it is possible, okay, but nevertheless it's a very
tiny concern and therefore we're not worried about it. So the important
thing about this is that it reminds us that the concern of
שלא לשמה shelo lishma was never a real concern. It was only
a concern that it would be a basis for a husband to
challenge the גט, get? if it was a problem that the husband
would change his mind or just want to make life, you know,
difficult for his wife. And therefore when the husband is delivering it,
it's not a concern. So for רבה, Rabba you still have to
say בפני נכתב befanai nechtav even though they now know the הלכה
halacha because we don't we want to keep things the way they
were, things might go back. But the husband doesn't have to say
it, and why doesn't he have to how about לשמה lishma concerns?
So the לשמה lishma. concerns are really not concerns about לשמה. lishma.
They're really concerns about the husband. So when the husband is delivering
it, he doesn't have to say it. Yes.
Could you say something more about the requirements of לשמה lishma, with
the writing of the גט?
get, That's going to be a whole פרק perek about that. We're
not so right now I'm going to say no. Why? Because I
mean no.
Right. Okay, now.
תא שמע. Ta shema. Come and hear. דבעי מיניה שמואל מרב הונא.
dbaei minei Shmuel meRav Huna. שמואל Shmuel asked from רב הונא. Rav
Huna. שנים שהביאו גט ממדינת הים. shnayim sheheviu get mimedinat hayam. Two
people bring. Remember that was one of our נפקא מינה. nafka minas.
Two people bring. They don't have it's not a problem of validating
signatures because they're basically testifying that the husband wrote it, you know,
sent them. So there's no concern that it was forged. But we
would we assume according to רבה Rabba, you would still have to
be concerned of לשמה. lishma. So two people brought a גט get,
ממדינת הים. צריכים שיאמרו בפנינו נכתב ובפנינו נחתם tzrichim sheyomeru bifnenu nechtav
uvifnenu nechtam or
oh, okay צריכים שיאמרו בפנינו נכתב ובפנינו נחתם או אין צריכים? tzrichim
sheyomeru bifnenu nechtav uvifnenu nechtam o ein tzrichim? Do they have to
say it or not? אמר ליה, Amar leh, he said to him,
אין צריכים. ein tzrichim. They don't have to. Now this isn't a
תנא, tanna, this is an אמורא, amora, but
okay. ומה אלו יאמרו בפנינו גירשה מי לא מהימני? uma ilu yomru
bifnenu gershah mi lo meheimni? If they had said that she was
divorced in front of us they'd be believed. So they're certainly believed
to say that the husband, you know, sent us to deliver this
גט get and he wrote the גט. get, So again it eliminates
any concern of עדות, edut, but it doesn't eliminate any concern of
לשמה. lishma,
So the גמרא Gemara says, לרבה ניחא לרבא קשיא. leRabba nicha leRava
kashya. Good for רבה, Rabba not good for רבא. Rava הכא במאי
עסקינן? דלמדו. Delamdu. Back to that. Okay, so now they know the
laws of לשמה, lishma so now it's no longer an issue. The
גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי, i hachi, if that's true, חד נמי.
chad nami. So even when one person delivers a גט, get, don't
have him say בפני נכתב, bifnei nichtav, just get it validated. גזירה
שמא יחזור דבר לקלקולו. gezeirah shema yachzor davar lekalkalah. We're afraid things
will slide back. Does this sound familiar? אי הכי, I hachi, if
we're afraid things will slide back and we continue to insist on
it, בי תרי נמי. bei terei nami. How about two? So they
have to still say it. No, בי תרי דמייתי גיטא מילתא דלא
שכיחא ומילתא דלא שכיחא לא גזרו בה רבנן. bei terei dmaisei gita
milta dlo shechicha umilta dlo shechicha lo gazru beh rabbanan. No, two
people bringing a גט get is unusual and the Rabbis didn't insist
on it in unusual cases. גמרא Gemara says one minute. והא אשה
דלא שכיחא? veha ishah dlo shechicha? How about a woman bringing her
own גט? get דתנן האשה עצמה מביאה גיטה ובלבד שצריכה לומר בפני
נכתב ובפני
נחתם. detnan haishah atzmah mevia gita bilvad shetzricha lomar bifnei nechtav uvifnei
nechtam. So a woman has to say it, that's unusual. שליחות shlichus.
no, we want to make one rule. Okay, you want to make
one rule, we're back to the old question. When two people bring
the גט, get let them have to say בפנינו נכתב. bifnenu nechtav.
So תוספות Tosafos again says שלא תחלוק בשליחות. shelo tachlok bishlichus. Funny
that רש״י Rashi isn't saying this. Okay, anyway, now תוספות Tosafos four
lines down in the wide lines, פירוש בשליחות דחד. peirush bishlichus dechad.
When it's one person bringing a גט, get that's that's where we're
going to say you have to say it. Okay, דגזרינן חד דלא
שכיח אטו חד דשכיח בי תרי אטו חד לא גזרינן. degazrinan chad
dlo shechiach atu chad dshechiach bei terei atu chad lo gazrinan. Two
people bringing a גט get is a fundamentally different type of a
thing. It is true they're שלוחים, shlichim, they are delivering the גט,
get but when two people bring it, it also has a different
feel to it. It's like about עדות edut and it's not just
about
agency. Therefore what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going back and saying
is, you know, okay, this is a case again we're not concerned
of לשמה lishma *lishma*, but we're gonna say in a normal case
of שליחות shlichus, *shlichus*, we're gonna keep on being concerned about it
because we're afraid things will slide back, but in a case of
two people, which is fundamentally different than a normal שליחות shlichus, *shlichus*,
you know, not just experientially different but like it's עדות *edus* and
not just שליחות *shlichus*, that's a case where we'll allow you just
to accept the validation and not to need the בפני נכתב bifnei
nichtav. ובפני נחתם *befanay nichtav u-vefanay nechtam*.
You had a question אבי *Abi*? Do you think this- didn't we
determine earlier that this requirement is דרבנן d'rabbanan *derabanan* already? Yeah. So
how can Joseph say that we're גזרינן חדא *gazrinan chada*?
You mean גזירה gezeirah לגזירה *gezerah le-gezerah*? Yeah, we make גזירה gezeirah
לגזירה *gezerah le-gezerah* all the time. Okay, yes.
Anyway, דרבנן *derabanan* is not the same as a גזירה gezeirah *gezerah*
because if it's a concern about the husband and social problems, we
could still try to protect that. Anyway, it's a form also of
a לא lo, פלוג *lo plug*, not גזירה לגזירה *gezerah le-gezerah*. But
yes.
I think I've lost how we're not concerned if it's just one
person bringing it, you can't say that it was signed or written
in front of me. Right. Why aren't we concerned it's forged?
No, it says, it says you don't as long as you get
it validated, you don't have to work—yeah, yeah, yeah. Exactly. And that's
why when two people bring it, that's an implicit validation. Okay, yeah.
לשמה lishma *lishma* means we're concerned about whether they know the rules
of doing it?
Well, you could see that as just representative of the rules in
general. תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* raised that question. Or is it no, very
specifically there's a concern of knowing this הלכה halacha? *halacha* that you
have to have the husband and the wife in mind when you're
like writing the גט get. *get*.
So how does that relate to the phrase written before, that's what
I'm trying to understand.
Oh,
so that we discussed on the first דף daf *daf*. רש"י *Rashi*
says either when you say it was written in front of me,
we inquire and find out more details to determine it was לשמה
lishma. *lishma*, or when he's saying that, if he knows he has
to say that, then it means that he understands what this is
all about, so we read that as an implicit testimony to it
was written in front of me like the right way. But yes,
that was a right, yeah, yeah. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says we're
still- this is all still a רבה Rabba *Rabbah*. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says אי הכי ei hachi, *i hachi*, if that's true,
that we're going to say a לא lo, פלוג *lo plug* and
always require it, so בעל ba'al נמי *baal nami*, the husband also
should have to say it, especially if there used to be these
לשמה lishma *lishma* concerns. אלא Ella, מאי תניא *ela mai tanya*, why
do we teach in a ברייתא braita *braita*: הוא עצמו שהביא גטו
אינו צריך לומר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם *hu atzmo sheheivi gito eino
tzarich lomar befanay nichtav u-vefanay nechtam*, he doesn't have to say it.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says טעמא מאי *tama mai*, you know
why the רבנן *rabbanan* said you had to say it, it's not
really a real לשמה lishma, *lishma* concern, it's really a husband concern.
דילמא אתי בעל ומערער ati ba'al u'm'ar'er ופסיל ליה *dilma ati baal
u-mearer u-fasil lei*. The concern is he'll use it as an excuse
to challenge the גט get, *get*. השתא מינקט נקט ליה בידיה *hashta
minkat nakat lei biyadei*, here he's bringing it in his own hands,
אי אתי ומערער ליה *ei ati u-mearer lei*, we think he's now
going to challenge it? So therefore that's why in that when the
husband brings it we don't have to worry about לשמה lishma *lishma*
and we certainly because it's not going to be challenged and we
certainly don't have to worry about forgery because he's delivering it. Okay.
תא שמע *ta shma*. Yes.
You said something very quickly a minute ago that agency or like
עדות *edus*. So really every case where there's one person bringing, it's
really more תורת שליחות *torat shlichus* than it is תורת עדות *torat
edus*.
Of course, yeah, exactly.
The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* uses a language of עד eid, אחד *ed
echad* as it were.
Where did it use the language of עד eid?
אחד *ed echad*? Exactly. It does, but it's always המביא *hameivi*.
Even when right, even when two people bring it, they're—they have to
also be שליחים *shlichim* because if you're not a שליח shaliach *shaliach*,
you're not empowered to deliver the גט get, *get*. Right, just that
they're also עדים *edim*. Right. Okay, so good. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this. תא שמע *ta shma*. המביא גט get. ממדינת
הים ונתנו לה u-nesanu lah, *hameivi get mi-medinat ha-yam u-nesano lah*, you
brought a גט get, *get* from ממדינת הים *mi-medinat ha-yam* and you
gave it to her, ולא אמר לה velo amar lah בפני נכתב
ובפני נחתם *velo amar lah befanay nichtav u-vefanay nechtam*, you didn't say
it was written and signed in front of me. אם נתקיים בחותמיו
כשר ואם לאו פסול pasul. *im nitkayem be-chotmav kasher ve-im lav pasul*.
So this is much easier than the אינו יכול *eino yachol* which
became a bizarre case. This one's it's after the fact. You gave
it to her and you forgot to say it. You know what?
Still okay, just go ahead and validate the signatures. So once again,
a clear statement that the real concern is validating the signatures. Okay,
but but if you didn't get the signatures validated, we won't let
the- we won't accept the גט get, *get*. Okay. הוי *hevei* from
here you see לא הוכרח לומר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם להחמיר עליה
lehachmir aleha. *lo huchrach lomar befanay nichtav u-vefanay nechtam le-hachmir aleha*, they
weren't trying to be strict on her to make it like oh
my god you didn't say it that's it you can never use
the גט get *get*. No, אלא להקל עליה *ela le-hakeil aleha*, we're
trying to go easy on her to give her an alternative to
getting validated signatures. But if it was given and you didn't say
it, there's still a way to deal with it, just go validate
the signatures. Okay. Once again, that's the- that's the statement.
Once again, לרבא ניחא לרבה קשיא *le-Rava nicha le-Rabbah kashya*. It's great
for רבא Rava *Rava*, it's all about the signatures. What about רבה
Rabba *Rabbah*? Whatever happened to the need of לשמה lishma *lishma*? הכא
במאי עסקינן *hacha b'mai askinan* לאחר שלמדו le'achar shelamdu? *le-achar she-lamdu*. Once
again, no, לשמה lishma *lishma* is no longer a concern and we're
okay just to validate. ואמרת גזירה שמא יחזור דבר לקלקולו shema yachzor
davar l’kilkulo *ve-amarta gezerah shema yachzor davar le-kilkulo*? But you said that
we- we still keep things in place, we still need the testimony
of לשמה lishma *lishma* because we're afraid that things might get back
to the old ways. So גמרא Gemara says, alright, כשנישאת, kesheniseit, it
would be a case that she already got married, basically it's like
בדיעבד. bedieved. So therefore you're right, we should insist on the testimony.
We shouldn't say validating the signatures is suffices. We should insist on
testimony of לשמה. lishma In a case where the guy was a
חרש, there was no option. But here where he could have, you
know, said it, he could have seen it, he could have said
it, he was being sloppy. So if you say okay, we're not
just going to go ahead and so trivially, like we have to
be serious about this requirement, buddy, I'm sorry, you're sloppy, it's no
good. We need testimony about לשמה, lishmah okay, even though now it's
no longer an active problem, it used to be a problem. So
how are we going to let it be okay בדיעבד? bedieved? So
the גמרא's Gemara answer is it doesn't seem a simple בדיעבד bedieved
would be enough, but we're talking about a major בדיעבד. bedieved. She
already got married. So if she already got married, she remarried, right,
she remarried a different person. Yes. So she already married a different
person, okay, and in this type of a case, right, we're gonna
go back to that... well now we can see that at least
like right now לשמה lishmah isn't an issue. So okay, if she's
already got married, we're gonna drop our לשמה lishmah insistence because it's
really not an issue these days, and we're only going to focus
on the need of witnesses. Okay, yeah. In some sense...
somehow
I can't figure out in the לשמה lishmah issue, the אתי בעל
ba'al. ומערער seems to be part of the לשמה. lishmah Yes. And
it's not just they knew they had to write it for this
man for this woman, but the בעל ba'al wasn't going to come
later and create...
No. The point is that what the גמרא Gemara said before is
that the concern about that they did it according to the הלכה
halachah requirement is really not a major concern. We are pretty darn
confident that they did it correctly in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, not
just לאחר שלמדו, le'achar shelamdu always that was the case. But we're
concerned that the husband will use this as a... you know, as
an excuse to challenge the גט, get? as a pretext. That's what
we're concerned about.
So why does the whole thing with
לאחר שלמדו?
le'achar shelamdu Yeah. So presumably לאחר שלמדו le'achar shelomdu. means after everybody
knows it in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz it won't even be a
pretext. Right now there are some people in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz.
that get it wrong. So now it could be used as a
pretext by the בעל.
ba'al The husband
is going to come and say this גט get was done incorrectly.
So we're going to say to him, what what what are you
talking about? They know what they're doing in חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz
It came from a
בית דין.
beit din. So it was done...
right, now if there are still some places in חוץ לארץ that
there are a few בתי דינים batei dinim out there that don't
know what they're doing, then you'll be able to make a legitimate
challenge. But if it's a place that now everyone now knows what
they're doing, then you've lost your pretext.
And also what he's doing is the man is doing the due
diligence to make sure the בעל ba'al is committed to it.
If he changed...
I'm not understanding.
It's not just the writing and the wording?
No, no, no. The שליח... shaliach well that is true that the
גמרא Gemara sort of said that the שליח shaliach is not going
to want to have his statement challenged, so he's going to be
sure, pretty sure the בעל is committed. Right, but no, that's not
the basic point. The basic point is that if we know that
it's written by the בעל because the signatures are validated or the
שליח shaliach is testifying to that, and either we know it was
לשמה lishmah. because the שליח shaliach testified to it or because there's
no real concern of לשמה, lishmah, then the husband has no basis...
he doesn't even have a pretext for challenging it. But at a
time if the שליח shaliach didn't testify לשמה lishmah, and there were
genuine places out there that didn't know, the husband has a pretext.
And that's the problem. We have to close off that pretext.
Okay, alright. So now the question is is that if we're gonna
say that even לאחר שלמדו le'achar shelomdu, we're going to insist on
it because of keeping things the way they were, the גמרא Gemara
says we're not going to
just בדיעבד... bedieved... you know, move on. But so how is it
that we allow things to be validated and not continue to insist
on it? So the גמרא Gemara. says, okay, it's a real בדיעבד,
bedieved, לאחר שנישאת, le'achar sheniseit, then we'll accept the fact that we
don't really need לשמה lishmah. anymore, I mean the לשמה lishmah testimony
anymore. The גמרא Gemara says אי הכי, if it's after she got
married, הא דקתני בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם להחמיר לא להקל, ha de'katni
bifnai nichtav uvifnai nechtam lehachmir lo lehakeil, we're only trying to go
easy on her, right? That statement makes a lot of sense if
it says oh, if you want to validate it's fine, we're only
trying to make it easier. But if we're not just trying to
validate it, we actually need other testimony of לשמה lishmah and we're
not gonna let you get married without that... so the גמרא says
משום דניסית. mishum deniseit.
The reason we're allowing it is because it's בדיעבד bedieved and she
got married, not because we really are okay with other witnesses. So
the גמרא says no, הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this is what it
means. וכי תימא להחמיר ותיפוק, vechi teima lehachmir veseipuk, if you want
to say even now that she's married we should be... not be
okay with it and be strict and demand she gets divorced? No.
הא דקתני בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם להחמיר לא להקל. ha de'katni bifnai
nichtav uvifnai nechtam lehachmir lo lehakeil. At the end of the day,
this statement is not going to be so strict on her
to force her to get divorced because the need of לשמה lishmah
testimony is not so great. Okay, still it's a much weaker read
of that point. The point is much more simply said as, you
know, you want to get rid of... be my guest, we were
only trying to make things easier, right? This way it's sort of
saying, oh well, we're not going to be so strict about בפני
נכתב if you already got married, you know, and we know that
it's validated, then we don't have to be so strict about about
the לשמה lishmah about the לשמה lishmah testimony. Okay, and now the
גמרא adds and
now here
Rashi takes out the word איבעית אימא iba'is eima but Tosafot has
them and I'm going to read it with איבעית אימא iba'is eima
cause I think it's a more satisfying read. And איבעית אימא, iba'is
eima, so that's one explanation, okay, which is that she already got
married. But איבעית אימא, iba'is eima, if you want you could say
that the following. I'm sorry, I'm sorry. That's after she got married
but we're talking about a special case of לאחר שלמדו. le'achar shelomdu,
But איבעית אימא, iba'is eima, but if you want you could go
further and say טעמא מאי דלמא אתי בעל ומערער ופסיל ליה. ta'ama
mai dilma ati ba'al u'm'ar'er u'pasil leh. Look, the whole reason that
we were concerned was that the husband was going to come and
invalidate it, the pretext. השתא בעל לא קא מערער אנן קיימינן ומערערינן
ליה? hashta ba'al lo ka m'ar'er anan kayiminan u'm'ar'arinan leh? Look, the
husband isn't challenging it, why are we going to make problems? So
we're not trying to make her life difficult. Now what the Tosafot,
right, so that's actually a better read of the statement, right? The
statement is like it's saying, look, we were not trying to make
her life difficult, we weren't trying להחמיר עליה. It wasn't like we
said, oh, the גט get. might not be good, you might not
be able to get remarried. No, no, no, we're not trying to
make her life difficult. We're trying to protect her against a possible
challenge from the husband. Okay, so since the purpose of it was
to protect the interests of the woman, it's a very interesting way
of looking at it, right? Are we trying to protect הלכה? halachah
Oh, can't let this גט get be given, it might be פסול.
pasul. Okay, if that's true, then we have to worry about that
after she got married too, right? Because we're concerned that the גט
get really might be פסול. pasul. But if what we're saying is,
no, no, no, we're not concerned the גט get, is פסול. We're
just concerned about the husband's challenge. So this is really about protecting
her interests. So if we're here to protect her interests and now
she's remarried, then the best way to protect her interests is to
leave this alone at this point, right? So that's a very powerful
statement, right? You know, that even the לשמה lishmah issue is just
because of the husband and protecting her interests. So we are not
going to insist on this once she got remarried. And Tosafot says
according to that answer, that would be even before לאחר שלמדו, right?
Even when לשמה lishmah was a real concern, but at the end
of the day, it was not a real concern that would have
made us חז"ל chazal
like demand, you know, for its own sake like demand it, it's
only enough of a concern because of concern of protecting the
woman's interests. Okay, so even when it really is an issue, we're
not going to insist on it once she's
married because then it's more in her interest to leave it alone
assuming that it's been validated, assuming that it's, right, that's all the
case. If the שליח shaliach, did not say it, then as long
as he validates it, it gets validated, it's okay. The signatures. If
the signatures weren't validated, then yes, then that would be something to
be more concerned about.
Exactly, exactly, but if we validated it, the לשמה lishmah? concern is
protecting her interests and therefore better here to just leave it alone.
Okay, so now the גמרא says like
this: what if the husband brought
it and he did not say anything?
He doesn't have to say anything, exactly, because we're not concerned then.
But the validation of the signatures doesn't have to be validated. He
gave it, right, so that's what it said before. Okay. So now
the גמרא says this debate of רבה Rabbah and רבא is דפליגי
דרבי יוחנן ורבי יהושע בן לוי. di'pligi d'Rabbi Yochanan v'Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi. It's a debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי יהושע
בן לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. חד אמר לפי שאין בקיאין לשמה
וחד אמר לפי שאין עדים מצויין לקיימו. chad amar lefi she'ein beki'in
lishma v'chad amar lefi she'ein edim metzuyin l'kaymo. One says one, one
says the other. תסתיים, tistayem, let's conclude רבי יהושע בן לוי הוא
דאמר לפי שאין בקיאין לשמה. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi hu d'amar lefi
she'ein beki'in lishma. He was the one who said לשמה. lishmah How
do we know this? דרבי שמעון בר אבא אייתי גיטא לקמיה דרבי
יהושע בן לוי. d'Rabbi Shimon bar Abba aiti gita l'kamei d'Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi.
Rabbi Shimon bar Abba brought a גט get in the presence of
רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, he was like on
the בית דין, beis din, רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi, or whatever, he was the head of the town and he
said or the rabbi of the town and אמר ליה amar leh
he said to him, "צריך אני לומר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם או
לא? tzarich ani lomar befanai nechtav u'befanai nechtam o lo? Do I
have to say it, do I have to say it or not?
I mean I know there's this משנה mishnah but are we still
doing this thing?" So אמר ליה amar leh so he said to
him, "לא צריכת. lo tzrichet. No, you don't have to say it.
לא אמרו אלא בדורות הראשונים, lo amru ela b'doros harishonim, they only
said it in the early generations, שאין בקיאין לשמה, she'ein beki'in lishma,
that people were not so careful about לשמה, lishmah, אבל בדורות האחרונים
aval b'doros ha'achronim in these later generations, דבקיאין לשמה d'beki'in lishma that
everybody knows," there's how the גמרא got the phrase לאחר שלמדו, right,
in these later generations that people know the law of לשמה, "לא,
you don't have to say
it." Okay, so the whole גזרה gezeirah goes away. So the גמרא
says תסתיים, tistayem, good, that was a good proof that רבי יהושע
בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi is about לשמה. But now we've
got a little bit of a problem, which is what ever happened
to validating the signatures? Okay, this really sounds like the one who
says לשמה only is concerned of לשמה and is not concerned with
anything else. And once לשמה goes away the whole thing goes away.
So that's what bothers the גמרא. וליטעמיך, u'l'ta'amecha, wait a minute, does
this make sense that רבה סבר לה כרבא? savar lah k'Rava? We
said that רבה agreed to רבא and presumably that means that we
said that you can't hold a לשמה only position because of the
evidence we brought earlier, nobody can hold of a לשמה only position.
And here it sounds like he's holding
of a לשמה only position. ועוד, V’od, and also, this goes against
the other thing we said earlier, which was that even after they,
you know, the things changed, we still keep the גזירה in place.
So the obvious answer is, okay, it does go against everything you
said earlier, you know? There really is a position that only holds
of לשמה and does not hold and holds that things can change.
But the גמרא says, no, we made our whole argument earlier, we
came to those conclusions, how do you explain what's going on here
that he seems to only be worried about לשמה? So the גמרא
says, here's how the גמרא answers that problem in one stroke. אלא
רב שמעון בר אבא איניש אחריני הוה בהדיה. Ella Rav Shimon bar
Abba inish achrini havah behadeih. He wasn't alone. There was actually two
people bringing a גט. get Okay? והא דלא חשיב ליה, V’ha d’lo
chashiv leih, the reason it didn't mention the other guy with him
bringing the גט, get משום כבודו דרב שמעון, mishum kevodo d’Rav Shimon,
cause if, you know, if you've got רב שמעון Rav Shimon and
John Doe, you're not going to say, oh, רב שמעון Rav Shimon
and John Doe, you know, the Lubavitcher Rebbe and Chaim Yankel came
to, brought a גט, get right?
So he rose from the grave and brought a גט. Get Anyways,
so alright, so you didn't mention the other guy. But how does
that solve the problem? אה, Ah, cause if there's two people, there's
no need to validate the signatures. Right? אה, Ah, but what about
the fact that even if things change, we keep the גזירה in
place? אה, but two people, לא שכיח, lo shechiach, two people is
not a classic case of שליחות. So we have managed to solve
that because since we laid out earlier that when two people bring
a גט, get, even according to the whole רבה יסודא דרבא yesoda
d’Rava and the גזירה is still in place and all of that,
we allow that when two people bring a גט, get you don't
need to say it.
Takes it completely out of תורת השליחות Torat ha-shlichus and into תורת
העדות. Torat ha-eidus.
Well, I wouldn't say out of שליחות, it's still שליחות, but whatever,
you right, you don't have that old like
paradigm doesn't apply.
Exactly. So you're able to say you don't need to validate signatures
and you're not concerned of שמא יחזור דבר לקלקולו because it's an
unusual case. פיין. Fine. איתמר. Itmar. Now we finally switch gears a
little bit. Okay. בפני כמה נותנה לה. Bifnei kamah n’tanah lah. פו.
Phew. Alright. So we've figured out all the reasons, the שליח shaliach,
has come, he's got his גט get in hand. In front of
how many people does he deliver this גט? get Because he's testifying
בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, he has to testify in front of somebody.
So at least two witnesses we would assume. So in front of
how many people does he give it?
So רבי יוחנן ורבי חנינא, Rabbi Yochanan v’Rabbi Chanina, it's a debate
of רבי יוחנן ורבי חנינא. Rabbi Yochanan v’Rabbi Chanina. חד אמר בפני
שנים וחד אמר בפני שלשה. Chad amar bifnei shenayim v’chad amar bifnei
shloshah. In front of one says two and one says three. תסתיים
דרבי יוחנן הוא דאמר בפני שנים. Tistayeim d’Rabbi Yochanan hu d’amar bifnei
shenayim. Let's assume that it's רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says two. How
do you know this? דרחבי בר רב חסדא אייתי גיטא לקמיה דרבי
יוחנן. D’Rachavei bar Rav Chisda ayiti gita l’kamei d’Rabbi Yochanan. רחבי בר
רב חסדא Rachavei bar Rav Chisda brought a גט get, in front
of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. ואמר ליה, V’amar leih, and רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said to him, זיל הבה לה באפי תרי. Zil havah
lah b’apei try. Go say, go give it to her, לא, באפי
תרי, b’apei try, go give it to her in the presence of
two witnesses. ואימא להו, V’eima lehu, and say to the witnesses, note
here the להו, lehu, to the witnesses, בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. It
was it was written and signed in front of me. So very
clear that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan holds two witnesses, he said go
give it in front of two. תסתיים. Tistayeim. That's a good proof.
Okay. Now what's that what's the debate of two and three about?
לימא בהא קמיפלגי. Leima b’ha kamifligi. Let's say this is the debate.
דמאן דאמר בפני שנים קסבר לפי שאין בקיאין לשמה. D’man d’amar bifnei
shenayim kasavar lefi she-ein beki’in lishmah. If it's about two, then it's
about testifying that it was done לשמה and you only need to
testify in front of witnesses. But if it's about validating the signatures,
how many people do you think you need to do the validation
of witnesses? Where, in front of a court, right? Okay, but ומאן
דאמר בפני שלשה, u-man d’amar bifnei shloshah, but if
you say three, קסבר לפי שאין עדים מצויין לקיימו. kasavar lefi she-ein
eidim metzuyin l’kayemo. It's about validating the signatures and that needs to
be done in a court. That makes sense. But הגמרא the Gemara
says one minute, תסבור, Tisbor, does that really make any sense? הא
רבי יהושע בן לוי אמר לפי שאין בקיאין לשמה. Ha Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi amar lefi she-ein beki’in lishmah. We just proved above in
the debate of רבי יוחנן ורבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yochanan v’Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi that רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
is the one who said לשמה, which implicitly shows that רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan is the one who said אין עדים מצויין לקיימו. ein
eidim metzuyin l’kayemo. רבי
יוחנן אמר לפי שאין עדים מצויין לקיימו. Rabbi Yochanan amar lefi she-ein
eidim metzuyin l’kayemo. That shows that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan holds it's
about validating signatures. Okay, so if it's about validating signatures, he should
have said three. והכא היכי אמר רבי יוחנן בפני שנים? V’hacha heichi
amar Rabbi Yochanan bifnei shenayim? So how could he say two is
enough? And not only that, ועוד, V’od, הא רבה יסודא דרבא. ha
Rabbah yesoda d’Rava. We just got through proving, which we're not going
to give up, that everybody agrees it's about signatures. So if everybody
agrees you gotta validate the signature, how can anybody say you need
less than three? Right, two is enough. So הגמרא the Gemara says
okay, אלא דכולי עלמא בעינן עדים מצויין לקיימו. Ella d’kulei alma ba’inan
eidim metzuyin l’kayemo. פיין. Fine. Everybody agrees you need to validate the
signatures. והכא בשליח נעשה עד ועד נעשה דיין קמיפלגי. V’hacha b’shaliach na’aseh
eid v’eid na’aseh dayan kamifligi. The question is, and here it does
get the different issues of the labels of שליח, shaliach עד, eid
and דיין. dayan. Okay, you're the שליח, shliach you're giving the גט.
get? Can you at the same time you're giving the גט get
be part of the בית דין beis din that is accepting your
testimony of validating the signatures? Okay. Now, on the one hand, what
we already have is you switch hats from being a שליח shliach
to being a witness, right? I am delivering the גט get and
I am testifying about the validity of the signature. That's שליח נעשה
עד. shaliach na’aseh eid. I'm already becoming a witness.
Now this of course seems completely absurd, but maybe it's something that
we allow in a like a special case like this and it's
only a דרבנן case and so on, right? דאורייתא D'oraisa you don't
need to validate the signatures, so that's what we're going to look
at.
So one guy counts as two, so you get three.
Exactly. He doesn't count as two, or I'm both a שליח shliach
and an עד, eid, so I'm two of the three. Right, dual
identity.
Right, but if we go to needing to be on the בית
דין, beis din, but why isn't it just a question of can
a שליח shliach also be an עד?
eid, Well, he definitely is an עד because he's testifying to the
validity of the signatures, right? And now the question is how could
it be that you only need to deliver it before two if
you need a בית דין? beis din? And the answer is well
look, the same way we let him switch hats and be an
עד, let's him switch hats again and be on the בית דין
beis din for his own testimony. Okay. So the גמרא says like
this.
Okay,
so the גמרא says like this. מאן
דאמר Man d'amar בפני שנים, bifnei shenayim, if he holds two, קסבר
kasavar שליח נעשה עד ועד נעשה דיין. shliach na'aseh eid ve-eid na'aseh
dayan. The same way you can become an עד, you can also
become a דיין dayan for your own testimony. ומאן דאמר Uman d'amar
בפני שלושה, bifnei sheloshah, if you hold three, קסבר kasavar שליח נעשה
עד ואין עד נעשה דיין. shliach na'aseh eid ve-ein eid na'aseh dayan.
No, you cannot become a דיין dayan for your own testimony. Okay,
that makes a lot of sense. But the גמרא says one minute,
וקיימא לן בדרבנן, ve-kaimalan bed'rabbanan, but we know that the accepted הלכה
is that for rabbinic types of testimony, which validating signatures is a
rabbinic testimony, so עד נעשה דיין. eid na'aseh dayan. That actually you
can, however bizarre that sounds. We actually know that it's accepted הלכה
that it would be possible for, in the case of validating signatures,
for the guy who testifies to be on the בית דין. beis
din. אלא, so everybody should say two. אלא הכא בהא קמיפלגי. Ella
hacha behai kamifligi. Here's the debate. מר סבר Mar savar כיון דאשה
כשירה להביא את הגט, kivan de-ishah kesherah lehavi es ha-get, a woman,
not necessarily the wife, any woman could bring a גט, get so
you don't want to always establish a principle that you only need
two witnesses present, because then people will think, will forget that it's
really you really need three. Right, if they get into the practice
that the שליח always delivers it before two, people are going to
forget that it's really about three and the שליח is counting as
one. And that's going to lead to a case where right, a
woman will bring a גט and she can't be a דיין, dayan,
ואתיא למסמך עלה, ve-atya le-mismech alah, and they'll rely on
her, okay, and therefore it won't, you know,
and she can't be a דיין, dayan, so that'll be a problem.
So that's why we want to always insist on three. ואידך, Ve-idach,
the other one will say, אשה מידע ידעי ולא סמכי עלה. ishah
meida yadiah velo samchi alah. No, they'll know, they'll know that that's
different and they won't rely on her to be counted as a
דיין. dayan. Okay, so that's the debate.
Business as usual.
I know. What are you going to do?
I would say don't worry, the woman would never forget that she
can't be a man. They won't forget.
Yeah, although the גמרא is saying they won't forget, but yeah, exactly.
It's times like these that we really miss Mifgal עליו השלום. alav
hashalom. Yeah, okay fine, woman can't be a דיין, dayan, moving on.
Okay, anyway.
תניא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן, Tanya kevasei de-Rabbi Yochanan, we פוסקין paskin like
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that you need two, it's only two. המביא
גט
ממדינת הים, ונתנו לה, and gave it to her, ולא אמר לה
בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, did not say
it, יוציא והולד ממזר. yotzi vehavlada mamzer. So now we first get
a very harsh statement, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says the גט's invalid if this wasn't said and the
kid is now a ממזר, mamzer, if she got remarried. Whatever the
consequences are, remember before we said that בדיעבד bedi'eved it would be
fine etc., רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is super strict. I don't care
if she's married and has kids, the divorce was invalid rabbinically at
least and the kids are ממזרים. mamzerim. So the גמרא says, וחכמים
אומרים, ve-chachamim omrim, wait a minute, and the Sages disagree. No, no,
no, אין הולד ממזר, ein havlada mamzer, please, please, we are not
making the kid a ממזר. mamzer. Now, כיצד יעשה, keitzad ya'aseh, what
do you want to do, how would you want to, what do
you want to do if you want to even allow her to
get married לכתחילה? l'chatchilah? First of all, בדיעבד bedi'eved the kid is
not a ממזר, mamzer, okay let's just start with that. But number
one, number two is what do you want to do for לכתחילה,
l'chatchilah, you want to allow her to get married with this גט
and the guy didn't say בפני נכתב, how do you, can you
address it? So we've already learned you can validate the signatures. But
let's say you can't find witnesses to validate the signatures. Is there
a way you can fix it after the גט has been delivered?
Okay, other than finding witnesses to validate the signatures. So here's what
you can do. כיצד יעשה, Keitzad ya'aseh, how can you fix it?
יטלנו הימנה, Yitlenu mimenu, ויחזור ויתננו לה ve-yachzir ve-yitlenu lah בפני שנים,
bifnei shenayim, ויאמר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. veyomar bifnei nichtav u-bifnei nechtam.
גט has to be said at the time of delivery, but just
deliver it again. Okay. Now a little bit of the problem is,
but she's already divorced if I delivered it once, you know. But
it's sort of like a ממאי נפשך. mima nafshach. If rabbinically we
don't see that as a legitimate, דאורייתא d'oraisa she's divorced and you
don't have to say it, if rabbinically we don't see that as
a legitimate delivery of the גט, we'll do it again with saying
it.
And if she got married before you re-delivered?
Well, the kids won't be ממזרים. mamzerim. Whether they're going to at
that stage what whatever else might be the consequence we don't know,
but the חכמים chakhamim are saying the kids are not going to
be ממזרים. mamzerim. Let's start with that. Okay? This is only a
rabbinic requirement. Alright? But regardless, if you want to allow her to
get married לכתחילה, lechatchila, you just go ahead and give it again
and say it. Now תוספות Tosafos, raises the question, right, when do
you, when is the time when you can no longer, when you
have to do a regiving of it? Because this makes it sound
like, well why not just say it now? Oh, I forgot to
say it yesterday, I'll just say it now. So it sounds like
it has to be said at the time of the giving. So
presumably it means like concomitant with the giving. So תוספות Tosafos says,
but one minute, remember the גמרא on the previous דף said that
the guy, after he gave it, all of a sudden became a
deaf-mute? So that sounds like you could give it after the giving.
So תוספות Tosafos's says, well, maybe תוך כדי דיבור, toch kedei dibbur,
maybe, you know, trying to figure out exactly what constitutes during the
time of the giving, it's not being precisely defined. If you look
at this little תוספות, Tosafos מאי יטלנה הימנה ויהבנא
לה, mai yitlena heimena ve-yahavna la, תוספות Tosafos says מכאן משמע שצריך
לומר בשעת נתינה, mikan mashma she-tzarich lomar besha'at netina, you can't say
it later, בפני נכתב. ממה דאמרה יטלנה הימנה, mima d'amra yitlena heimena,
you have to, right, take it away back from her, meaning תוספות's
point is if you think about the scene, it sounds like the
גט is still in her hands. It's not like it's tomorrow. It
sounds like the גט is still in her hands and you say
oh, take it back. I don't understand, the גט is still in
her hands, let me just say it now. No, it has to
be said ממש mamash at the time of being given. Okay? But
תוספות says והוא הדין לאחר נתינה תוך כדי דיבור, ve-hu ha-din le-achar
netina toch kedei dibbur, it is though true that תוך כדי דיבור
toch kedei dibbur would be okay דמהני, de-mahani, like a second after,
מדי קאמר לעיל שנתנו לה כשהיה פיקח ולא הספיקו לומר בפני נכתב
עד
שנשתתק. midei ka-amar le'eil she-natnu la keshe-hayah pike'ach velo hispiku lomar bifnei
nichtav ad she-nishtateik. Okay? So ממש mamash a second, two seconds after
is okay, but ten seconds after, no, you gotta regive it. Okay?
אבל לאחר כדי דיבור, aval le-achar kedei dibbur, after כדי דיבור, kedei
dibbur, מספקא ליה לרי, mesapka leh le-Ri, the רי Ri is uncertain
אי מהני כל זמן שעוסקין באותו עניין או לאו. i mahani kol
zeman she-oskin be-oto inyan o lav.
Let's say they're still talking about the גט, would that be enough
to be considered during the giving of the גט? Like you could
be hold, right? So the scene of יטלנה הימנה yitlena heimena
sounds like they're still standing there. So it sounds like not too
late, not too far after the giving it's too late. But when
is that too late time? Is the too late time after three
seconds? Or is the too late time after they stop dealing with
גט issues? You know, when they start talking about okay what movie
are you going to see tonight? That's when it becomes too late,
but as long as they're still talking about גט issues, maybe it's
not too late. So we don't know exactly what the time is.
Okay? או לאו. o lav. Now how about before the giving? Right,
there's three times: during, after, and before. How, can you say it
before you actually give, and if so, how much before? Okay? So
he says וקודם נתינה מספקא ליה לרי נמי ve-kodem netina mesapka leh
le-Ri nami אי מהני, i mahani, מדיתנן mi-detnan etc. etc. Okay? So
we don't, so תוספות is exactly timing this. During definitely yes, immediately
after תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur definitely yes, anytime before or
after that, like not exactly clear. Anyway, back to the גמרא. The
גמרא is bringing this out to prove the basic point of give
it to her בפני שנים, bifnei shenayim, that the ברייתא says that
you regive it in front of two, makes it very clear like
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that it's about two. Okay? So that's why
we brought this down. ויתננה לה בפני שנים ויאמר בפני נכתב ובפני
נחתם. ve-yitnena la bifnei shenayim ve-yomar bifnei nichtav u-vifnei nechtam. And now
we'll just end this point. ורבי מאיר משום דלא אמר בפני נכתב
ובפני נחתם יוציא והולד ממזר? ve-Rabbi Meir mishum dela amar bifnei nichtav
u-vifnei nechtam yotzi ve-ha-valad mamzer? Just because of that, the kid's gonna
be a ממזר? mamzer? I mean even if you get the גט
validated, and even if she's got remarried and has kids, you're going
to say the kids are ממזרים? mamzerim? אין! In! Yes! דרבי מאיר
לטעמיה, de-Rabbi Meir l'ta'ameih, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir goes according to his
reasoning, דאמר רב המנונא משמיה דעולא אמר היה רבי מאיר, d'amar Rav
Hamnuna mishmeih d'Ulla amar hayah Rabbi Meir, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir used
to say, כל המשנה ממטבע שטבעו חכמים בגיטין, kol ha-meshaneh mi-matbe'a she-tav'u
chakhamim be-gittin, anybody who changes from the basically like the coinage,
you know, that the חכמים chakhamim coined, like we say coining a
phrase, like the way they created a mold and you have to
operate within that mold, and if you step out of that mold,
היוציא והולד ממזר, hayotzi ve-ha-valad mamzer, gotta get divorced and the kid's
a ממזר, mamzer, like any mistake is a traumatic is a בדיעבד
bedi'avad mistake. Okay?
And we will stop with that right now, perfect end of a
discussion, pick up with this on Shabbat.